Inventory of the Truman Smith papers, 1893-2002
Hoover Institution Archives
Truman Smith papers
1893-2002
XX071
Hoover Institution Archives
27 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 4 microfilm reels (15.8 linear feet)
The Truman Smith papers (in part, photocopies) relate to the German army between World Wars I and II, national socialism in Germany, American military intelligence activities before and during World War II, and post-war American military policy. The collection is comprised of correspondence, memoirs, diaries, speeches and writings, intelligence reports, service records, printed matter, personal documents, photographs, and postcards; it also includes the papers of Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, wife of Truman Smith, and other family papers.
Smith, Truman.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1969, with increments added in 1974, 1978, 1979, 1980, 1981, 1993, 2010, and 2013.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Existence and Location of Originals note
In part, originals in: Herbert Hoover Presidential Library.
Biographical Note
1893 August 25 Born, West Point, New York
1915 Bachelor of Arts, Yale College
1916 Joined 12th Infantry Regiment of the New York National Guard
1916 June Ordered to the Mexican border to defend against Pancho Villa's army
1917 July 14 Married Katherine Alling Hollister
1917-1918 Commander, 4th Infantry, Company B (later Company A) in World War I, in France
1918 Instructor, U.S. Infantry School, Langres, France
1919-1920 Political advisor to the Officer in Charge of Civil Affairs at Koblenz, Germany
1920-1924 Assistant military observer and assistant military attaché, U.S. Mission and U.S. Embassy, Berlin, Germany
1928-1932 Instructor, Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia
1931-1935 Commanded 2nd Battalion of the 27th Infantry at the Schofield Barracks, Hawaii
1935-1939 Military attaché, U.S. Embassy, Berlin, German
1939-1946 German Specialist in Intelligence, General Staff (G-2), War Department
1948 Military Advisor to the Eberstadt (Armed Forces) Committee on the Hoover Commission
1970 October 3 Died, Fairfield, Connecticut
Scope and Content of Collection
The Truman Smith papers were received in several increments and are retained as they were originally received, with the exception of oversize photographs that were rehoused. Also included are the papers of Truman Smith's wife, Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, who accompanied her husband in his stays in Koblenz, Berlin, and elsewhere. A prolific writer, Katharine's memoirs, diaries, and correspondence provide insight into the family's interactions with German officials, life in Berlin between the wars, and her relationship with Smith.
Among the original documents in the Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, and 1980-1993 Increments series are photocopies of Truman Smith's papers at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library and Museum in West Branch, Iowa. Some of these copies are printed from the microfilm, which is also available in the collection.
Of particular note in the Correspondence series are original letters written by Charles Lindbergh to Truman Smith. Having come to Germany at Smith's invitation to observe the development of German aviation, Lindbergh's letters offer his frank impressions of the Luftwaffe and their capabilities. More formal analysis is available in Smith's reports to the War Department.
Among the original materials in the 1980-1993 Increments is a photo album containing postcards from the 1936 Berlin Olympics depicting Hitler, American athlete Jesse Owens, and other scenes from the newly built stadium. This increment also includes Katharine A. H. Smith's unpublished memoirs.
While stationed on the Mexican border during General Pershing's Mexican Expedition and as a commander of the 4th Infantry in German-occupied France during World War I, Smith wrote constantly to his family and to Katharine ( 2010 Increment). Although often personal in nature, these letters offer insight into Smith's understanding of the historical events which surrounded him and provide researchers with context to his future military career.
The papers also include manuscript copies of Smith's memoir "The Facts of Life" which was published in Berlin Alert: The Memoirs and Reports of Truman Smith (1984), edited by Robert Hessen as part of the Hoover Archival Documentaries series.
Throughout the collection, notes and annotations by Katharine Alling Hollister Smith and daughter Katharine T. Coley (née Smith, but known mostly as Kätchen) accompany photographs and correspondence to provide historical context to the documents. Original folders and folder titles were retained.
Germany. Heer.; Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; United States. Army--Officers.; Army wives--United States.; Germany--History--1933-1945.; Military attachés.; National socialism.; Secret service--United States.; United States--Military policy.; Women--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.
- Correspondence, 1935-1970 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Photocopies, unless otherwise noted.
  - Acheson, Dean (Washington, D.C.), 1964 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Air Force Historical Foundation (Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama), 1963 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Babb, James T. (New Haven, C.T.), 1957, 1960-1961, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Betts, Major General Thomas J. (Washington, D.C.), 1957 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Burnett, C., Colonel (Washington, D.C.), 1935, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Clark, Carter, General (Washington, D.C.), 1967 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Coulter, John B., Lieutenant Colonel (Washington, D.C.), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Coyne, David (Hoboken, N.J.), 1964 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Craig, Malin, General (Washington, D.C.), 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Crockett, James C., Captain (U.S. Embassy, Berlin, Germany), 1935 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Delaney, Edmund T. (New York, N.Y.), 1957 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Gotlieb, Howard B. (New Haven, C.T.), 1961 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Hanighen, Frank C. (Washington, D.C.), 1957 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Harding, Eleanor (Mrs. Forrest), 1969 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Harding, Forrest, Major General, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Knopf, Alfred, Jr. (New York, N.Y.), 1961 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Kromer, Leon B., Major General (Washington, D.C.), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Lamont, Betty (Mrs. Gordon), 1968 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Lee, Raymond E., Colonel (U.S. Embassy, Berlin, Germany), 1936 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Lindbergh, Charles A., Colonel, 1936 June-1942 February (Box-folder 1: 21)
    Includes 31 original letters from Lindbergh.
  - Mason, Frank E. (New York, N.Y.), 1964 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Mayer, Ferdinand L. (Bennington, V.T.), 1967 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - McCabe, E. R. W., Colonel (Washington, D.C.), 1938 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Murphy, Robert (New York, N.Y.), 1961 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Palmer, Paul ( Reader's Digest, Pleasantville, N.Y.), 1960 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Pappenheim, General von, undated (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Patch, J. (Mrs. Dorst), 1966 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Pogue, Forrest C. (Arlington, V.A.), 1969 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Reichenau, Walter (Munich, Germany), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Schell, Adolf von (Berlin, Germany), 1936 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Schell, Brigetta von (Mrs. Adolf), 1967 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Speidel, Hans, General (Rheinland, Germany), 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - St. George, Katherine (Mrs. George) (Washington, D.C.), 1964 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - U.S. Army, Department of the, Office of the Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence (Washington, D.C.) (second page missing), 1964 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - U.S. War Department (Washington, D.C.), code cablegram, 1938 September 27 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Van Voorst, M., Colonel (London, England), 1943 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Weckerling, John, Brigadier General (Washington, D.C.), 1951 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Wedemeyer, Albert C., General (Boyds, M.D.), 1964 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Willems, John M., Major General (Washington, D.C.), 1961 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Wood, O.S., Lieutenant Colonel (Washington, D.C.), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Young, Genevieve (Harper & Row, New York, N.Y.), 1961 (Box-folder 1: 42)
- Speeches and Writings, 1924-1956 (Boxes 1-3)
  Writings, memoranda, reports, notes, essays, and lectures, arranged alphabetically by title. Includes photocopies of materials from the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library in West Branch, Iowa.
  - "Activities of the Office of the Military Attaché, American Embassy, Berlin, Germany: August 1935 to April 1939," memorandum, undated; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 1: 43)
  - "Air Intelligence Activities. Office of the Military Attaché. American Embassy, Berlin, Germany, August 1935-April 1939: With Special Reference to the Service of Colonel Charles A. Lindbergh," report, 1956; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 44)
  - "Chemical Warfare and the Tactical Training of the Army: With Special Reference to Infantry," report, 1932; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 45)
  - "The Development of the Art of War in the Middle Ages and Renaissance," essay, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 46)
  - "Estimate of the German Political and Economic Situation," report, 1937; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 47)
  - "An Estimate of the Inner Political Situation," report, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 48)
  - "ETHE: A Tactical Study," by Truman Smith and Richard G. Tindall, lecture, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 49)
  - "Europe - October 1936: As Seen from Berlin," report, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 50)
  - "General Estimate as of Nov. 1, 1937," Military Intelligence Division report relating to the German Luftwaffe, Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 51)
  - "German Air Power: General Estimate as of Nov. 1, 1937" (extracts), 1937 October 25; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 52)
  - "Germany and Hitler," individual staff memorandum, 1933; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 53)
  - "Germany: Comments on Current Events, No. 3: The Pirow Hitler conversation," report, 1938; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 1: 54)
  - "Germany: Comments on Current Events, No. 8: Comments on European Situation," report, 1939; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Germany - Poland, Italy, Japan," essay, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Historical Map Problem: A German Operation on September 5, 1914," paper presented at The Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Historical Map Problem: An Operation of the 66th French Brigade, 1941 August 22," paper presented at The Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Hitler and the National Socialists," notebook and report of Captain Truman Smith, Infantry, U.S. Army, Assistant Military Attache, Berlin, Germany, describing a visit to Munich from November 15 to November 22, 1922, 1924; Photocopy (typescript). 2 copies. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "The Inner Political Situation in Germany, 1938 November 24," report, undated; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Joint Plans and Army Strategic Plans of Germany Just Prior to the World War," essay prepared for a course at the Army War College, by Subcommittee No. 2. Major Truman Smith, Infantry Chairman, Major B. S. DuBois, C.A.C., Major J.E. Jacobs, FA-Res., 1932-1933; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Panic," essay, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Party and Army, Germany - December 1937," essay, Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 9)
  - "Rosignol," essay, undated; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 2: 10)
  - "Strategic Survey of Germany," course at the Army War College, essay prepared by Subcommittee No. 1, Maj. Truman Smith, Chairman, et al., 1932-1933; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 2: 11)
  - Truman Smith, The Facts of Life: A Narrative With Documents, an unpublished autobiographical narrative, 1893-1946, undated; Photocopy (typescript). 155 pp. Illustrated with original photographs. 2 copies. (Folder 2: 12-13)
  - "War Potential and Intentions of European Axis Nations. Military Intelligence Division-Report: Germany (Political)" (Box-folder 3: 1-7)
    - "German Foreign Policy Under Hitler,", 1939 November 25; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 1)
    - "The Politico-Military Factor of the Rhineland Occupation,", 1936 March 20; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 2)
    - "The German Foreign Policy, May 1936,", 1936 May 7; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 3)
    - "Germany and Czechoslovakia - When?,", 1938 April 5; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 4)
    - "Czechoslovak Question,", 1939 August 8; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 5)
    - "The Czechoslovak Crisis,", 1938 September 1; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 6)
    - "The Future of Memel District,", 1939 October 28; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 7)
  - "War Potential and Intentions of European Axis Nations. Military Intelligence Division-Report: Germany (Combat)" (Box-folder 3: 8-12)
    - "The Militarization of the Rhineland,", 1936 March 9; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 8)
    - "The Expansion of the Active Army,", 1937 January 9; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 9)
    - "The German Fortress Area towards France and Luxemburg,", 1927 November 19; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 10)
    - "German Army Tendencies,", 1938 February 26; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 11)
    - "Fortifications-German West Front,", 1938 June 10; Photocopy (typescript) (Folder 3: 12)
- Subject File, 1936-1970 (Box 3)
  Letters, articles, clippings, and a deposition, arranged alphabetically by subject. Includes photocopies of materials from the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library in West Branch, Iowa.
  - Babb, James T. (Box-folder 3: 13-14)
    - Correspondence with Frank E. Mason (New York, N.Y.), Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 13)
    - Letters sent to Harold J. Gordon, Jr. (Amherst, M.A.), 1964; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 14)
  - Biography of Colonel Truman Smith, U.S. Army (Retired), undated; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 15)
  - German economy and German military power, unsigned deposition, Fairfield County, C.T., 1945; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 16)
  - Harding, General Forrest, newspaper clippings, 1886-1969?; Photocopy. (Folder 3: 17)
  - Lindbergh, Anne M. (Mrs. Charles), letters to Katherine Smith (Mrs. Truman), handwritten originals, letter is a photocopy, 1936-1941, 1970 October 18 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Lindbergh, Colonel Charles A., letter to Katherine Smith (Mrs. Truman), 1970 October 10; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Der Mensch, der Adolf Hitler hiess," Quick, Nr. 15, v.12.4.64., Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Orientation on the Written Monograph," lecture outline, undated; Photocopy (typescript). (Folder 3: 21)
  - Pogue, Forrest C. (Arlington, V.A.), correspondence with Colonel Edmund Delaney, 1969 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Smith, Kätchen (daughter of Truman Smith), letter to Anne M. Lindbergh, 1937 October 18; Original (handwritten). (Folder 3: 23)
  - U.S. Army, Department of Public Information Division, The Medal of Honor of the United States Army, Washington, D.C., G.P.O., 1938; Extract. (Folder 3: 24)
- 1980-1993 Increments, 1916-1992 (Boxes 4-16)
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith file, circa 1916-1946, 1981, undated (Boxes 4-7)
    - Memoirs, undated
      - "My Life, 1904-1914: Greenport, My Share of the American Dream," 119 p., undated (Folder 4: 1-2)
        2 copies
      - "My Life, 1916-1923: Who Won the War?," typescript (photocopy), 418 p., undated (Folder 4: 3-7)
      - "My Life, 1916-1923: Who Won the War?," typescript (photocopy), 418 p., undated (Folder 5: 1-3)
      - Diary, typescript (photocopy), 1916-1919 (Folder 5: 4)
        See also Box 22: "Diaries, vols. I-III, 1919"
      - "My Life: Years of Preparation, 1924-1935," photocopy, undated (Folder 5: 5-6)
      - "My Life, 1916-1923," typescript (photocopy), 418 p., undated (Folder 6: 1-3)
      - "My Life, August 1935-April 1939," bound volume, undated (Folder 6: 4)
      - Berlin, 1938, undated (Folder 6: 5)
      - "My Life: The War Years, 1939-1946," typescript (photocopy), 127 p., undated (Folder 6: 6)
      - "My Life: The War Years, 1939-1946," typescript (photocopy), undated (Folder 7: 1-2)
    - National Archives correspondence, 1981 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Postcards, 1931-1938, undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Photocopies of Truman Smith's papers at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library, West Branch, IA, 1919-1974 (Boxes 8-13)
    - Subject file, 1919-1974 (Boxes 8-11)
      - "Air Intelligence Activities...Berlin, 1935-1939,", 1953-1964
        - Correspondence, 1953-1964 (Box-folder 8: 1)
        - Bound volume (Folder 8: 2)
        - Lindbergh comments, 1955 (Folder 8: 3)
        - Lindbergh corrected manuscript
          - Pages 1-68 (Folder 8: 4)
          - Pages 69-118 (Folder 8: 5)
      - Army, 1928-1952
        - G-2 Division, 1941-1952 (Folder 8: 6)
        - Lectures at Fort Benning, 1928-1932 (Folder 8: 7)
        - Service School "Monographs,", 1932-1933 (Folder 8: 8)
      - B, general correspondence, 1941-1970, undated (Folder 8: 9)
      - C, general correspondence, 1946-1967 (Folder 8: 10)
      - Clippings (Folder 8: 11)
      - Germany G-2 reports, 1938-1939 (Folder 8: 12)
      - D-F, general correspondence, 1946-1970 (Folder 9: 1)
      - Faymonville, Philip R., 1970 (Folder 9: 2)
      - G, general correspondence, 1969-1970 (Folder 9: 3)
      - Germany
        - Army development, 1954-1956 (Folder 9: 4)
        - Military attaché correspondence, 1935-1938 (Folder 9: 5)
        - G-2 reports
          - 1935-1936 (Folder 9: 6)
          - 1937 (Folder 9: 7)
          - 1940-1945 (Folder 9: 8)
        - Photographs, 1934-1935, undated (Folder 9: 9)
          Photocopies
      - Guatemala and Communism, 1952-1954 (Folder 9: 10)
      - H, general correspondence, 1940-1970 (Folder 9: 11)
      - Hitler and the National Socialists, 1922-1924 (Folder 9: 12)
        - Correspondence, 1960-1961
        - Bound volume, photocopies
      - Hoover Commission, 1948-1949 (Folder 9: 13)
      - Hoover, Herbert, 1945-1964 (Folder 9: 14)
      - L, general correspondence, 1948-1968 (Folder 9: 15)
      - Lindbergh, Charles and Ann
        - Correspondence, 1936-1975 (Folder 9: 16)
        - Clippings, 1927-1964 (Folder 9: 17)
      - Lodge, John Davis, 1946-1962 (Folder 9: 18)
      - Luce, Clare Booth, 1945-1964, undated (Folder 9: 19)
      - M, general correspondence, 1940-1970 (Folder 9: 20)
      - Marshall, General George C., 1957-1969 (Folder 10: 1)
      - O-R, general correspondence, 1955-1972, undated (Folder 10: 2)
      - Russian Declaration of War on Japan -- G-2 Report, 1951-1969 (Folder 10: 3)
      - S, general correspondence, 1947-1967, undated (Folder 10: 4)
      - Smith, Kätchen correspondence
        - 1937 (Folder 10: 5)
        - 1938 (Folder 10: 6)
        - 1940-1941, undated (Folder 10: 7)
      - Smith, Truman
        - Biographical sketches (Folder 10: 8)
        - Clippings (Folder 10: 9)
        - Army service
          - Decorations, 1919-1948 (Folder 10: 10)
          - Orders, 1932-1956 (Folder 10: 11)
          - Retirement benefits, 1945-1974 (Folder 10: 12)
      - "Facts of Life," documents used and reproduced in memoir, photocopies, undated (Folder 11: 1)
      - "Truman Smith: 1893-1946, The Facts of Life: A Narrative with Documents," typescript, 154 pp. (Folder 11: 2)
      - Speidel, Hans, 1948-1970 (Folder 11: 3)
      - T, general correspondence (Folder 11: 4)
        Includes letters from George Tinkham (1947) and Paul Thompson (1969).
      - Taft, Robert, correspondence, 1945-1952 (Folder 11: 5)
      - Trudeau, Arthur, correspondence, 1955-1962 (Folder 11: 6)
      - W, general correspondence (Folder 11: 7)
        Includes letters from DeWitt Wallace, General Warlimont (1950), John Wheeler-Bennett, Don Willever (1970), Charles Willoughby (1946), Hugh Wilson (1946-1950).
      - Wedemeyer, Albert, correspondence, 1947 (Folder 11: 8)
      - Wood, Robert E. and Mrs., correspondence, 1945-1961 (Folder 11: 9)
      - Z, general correspondence and unidentified (Folder 11: 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 1945, undated (Folder 11: 11)
    - Writings and speeches, 1941-1967 (Box 11-13)
      - Bridgeport Chamber of Commerce, 1946 (Folder 11: 12-13)
      - "Strategicus" articles, 1941-1952 (Folder 11: 14-16)
      - "Strategicus" articles
        - Printed, 1941-1942 (Folder 12: 1)
        - Typed, 1941-1942 (Folder 12: 2)
      - "Hitler's Trick Gadgets, Unlimited,", 1946 (Folder 12: 3)
      - "La Abdicación del Estado-Mayor Alemán,", 1946 (Folder 12: 4)
      - "Nazi Strategy," Army War College, 1947-1948 (Folder 12: 5)
      - Letter to editor, Brideport Post, 1948 (Folder 12: 6)
      - Foreign Affairs roundtable, 1948 (Folder 12: 7)
      - Testimony, Senate, Armed Services Committee, 1948 (Folder 12: 8)
      - Radio debate with Norman Thomas (disarmament, etc.), 1948-1949 (Folder 12: 9)
      - "The Rise of German Air War Power: 1933-1939," Air War College, 1948-1949 (Folder 12: 10)
        3 copies
      - 4th of July address, 1949 (Folder 12: 11)
      - "Hoover Report," Republican Women's Club of Greenwich, 1949? (Folder 12: 12)
      - "Thoughts on the Defense of Europe,", 1950 (Folder 12: 13)
      - "Joseph Anthony Michaela,", 1950 (Folder 12: 14)
      - Political address, Westport Women's Club, 1950 (Folder 12: 15)
      - Book review, The Freeman: Europe Between the Acts, 1951 (Folder 12: 16)
      - Letters to Kätchen from Central America from Katharine A. H. Smith, 1952 (Folder 12: 17)
      - Impressions of Germany, 1955 (Folder 12: 18)
      - Germany, Virgin Islands memorandum, 1955 (Folder 12: 19)
      - "The Infamous Record of Soviet Espionage," Reader's Digest, 1960 (Folder 12: 20)
      - "Notes on a Lazy Winter" (Jamaica, Haiti, Puerto Rico), 1961 (Folder 12: 21)
      - Memorandum regarding Miracle on the Marne, 1961 (Folder 12: 22)
      - "A Summer at a Montana Dude Ranch,", 1962 (Folder 12: 23)
      - "Jungling as a Winter Sport,", 1963 (Folder 12: 24)
      - "Estimates of the Combat Value of the German Army,", 1963 (Folder 12: 25)
      - Germany, letters from, 1963 (Folder 12: 26)
        Includes photocopies and originals, with photographs
      - Latin American cruise, 1964 (Folder 12: 27)
      - "Not Much Rain in Spain,", 1965 (Folder 12: 28)
      - Smith to [Carter Weldon] Clark on Vietnam, 1967 (Folder 12: 29)
      - Truman Smith, miscellaneous writings, 1961-1968 (Folder 13: 1)
  - Photographs, negatives, and postcards, 1936-1939 (Box 13)
    - Three photo albums of postcards from Sweden, Denmark, and Paris, 1936-1939 (Folder 13: 2-4)
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1917-1992 (Box 14)
    - Letters to Kätchen from Germany, holograph drafts, 1963 (Folder 14: 1)
    - Letters to family, typed copies and carbons, 1919-1923 (Folder 14: 2-6)
    - Correspondence and writings, 1965-1977 (Folder 14: 7)